Finding Aid for John J. H. Schwarz Papers 1987-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John J. H. Schwarz Papers 1987-2002, 1999-2002
Schwarz, John J. H.
8 linear feet
Republican state senator from Battle Creek, Michigan, 1987-2002; legislative files documenting issues of higher education appropriations, state health concerns, and expenditure of monies received from lawsuit against the tobacco companies.
035 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Senator John J. H. Schwarz (donor no. 9289 ) and came to the library in December 2002.
The collection is open for research.
John J. H. Schwarz was born November 15, 1937 in Chicago, Illinois. Schwarz was raised and educated in Battle Creek, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan (1959) and from the Wayne State University Medical School (1964). He served with the US Navy in Vietnam, 1965-1966, as assistant naval attaché with the US embassy in Djakarta, 1966-1967, and then with the Central Intelligence Agency in southeast Asia, 1968-1970.
Returning to Battle Creek, Schwarz began his practice in otolaryngology-head and neck surgery. In addition, he involved himself in local government and politics. He was a member of the Republican State Committee, 1975-1976, a city commissioner, 1979-1985, and mayor of Battle Creek, 1985-1987. In 1986, Schwarz was elected to the Michigan State Senate representing the 24th senate district. He was reelected three times, then left office in 2002 due to the state's term limit restriction.
In the Senate, Schwarz served on various committees: appropriations, general government, higher education, and health policy among others. In 1993, he was elected president pro tempore of the senate, serving until he left the senate.
The papers represent a fragment of this state senator's career as much material had been discarded prior to the library's contact with the Schwarz office. Although some of the materials (mainly clippings) date to the period when he first came to Lansing in the mid-1980s, the great bulk of the collection dates from Schwarz's last term in office, 1999-2002. As might be expected, the files pertain to Schwarz's activities in the state senate, especially on issues of appropriations to the state's colleges and universities. There is also substantial information relating to current state health issues. Not present in these papers are materials relating to his activities outside the senate, campaigns for office, or his candidacy for governor in 2002. There are also no photographs or other visual materials in the collection.
The papers have been brought together in the following series: Higher Education; Health Issues; Other Issues; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Schwarz, John J. H.; Higher education and state--Michigan.; Legislators--Michigan.; Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; People Protecting Kids and the Constitution.; Republican Party (Mich.); Tobacco industry--Law and legislation--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Websites.; CD-ROMs.
- Higher education
  - Colleges and universities 1994-2002
    - Albion College (Box 1)
    - Central Michigan University (Box 1)
    - Community Colleges (general) (Box 1)
    - Detroit College of Law (proposed affiliation with Michigan State University) (Box 1)
    - Eastern Michigan University (Box 1)
    - Ferris State University (Box 1)
    - Grand Valley State University (Box 1)
    - Kalamazoo Community College (Box 1)
    - Lake Superior State (Box 1)
    - Michigan State University (Box 1)
    - Michigan Technological University (Box 1)
    - Northern Michigan University (Box 2)
    - Oakland University (Box 2)
    - Olivet College (Box 2)
    - Saginaw Valley State University (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - Wayne State University (Box 2)
    - Western Michigan University (Box 2)
  - Higher Education appropriation legislation
    - FY1999-FY2000 (Box 3)
    - FY2000-FY2001 (Box 3)
    - FY2002-FY2003 (Box 3)
  - Topical files
    - A-K (Box 4)
    - L-S (Box 5)
    - T-Z (Box 6)
- Health Issues
  - Abortion (Box 6)
  - Assisted suicide (Box 6)
  - Automated external defibrillator legislation (Box 6)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield (Box 6)
  - Certificate of Needs Standards (Box 6)
  - Chiropractors (Box 6)
  - Comprehensive Cancer Center. Interactive Kiosk Project (Box 6)
  - Controlled substances (Box 6)
  - Death and dying (Box 6)
  - Donated Dental Services (Box 6)
  - Drugs (Box 7)
  - Eugenics (Box 7)
  - Hospital issues-Oaklawn (Box 7)
  - Mail order prescriptions (Box 7)
  - Malpractice (Box 7)
  - Medicaid reimbursement (Box 7)
  - Michigan Peer Review Organization (Box 7)
  - Michigan Society for Medical Research (Box 7)
  - Nursing/nursing shortage (Box 7)
  - Poor citizens (Box 7)
  - Wayne State-diabetes (Box 7)
- Other Issues
  - People Protecting Kids and the Constitution (PPKC) 2002 (Box 7)
    (re use of tobacco settlement monies)
  - People Protecting Kids and the Constitution (PPKC) 2002 (Box 8)
  - Historic Preservation (Box 8)
  - Police Issues (Box 8)
  - Roads (Box 8)
  - Telecommunications legislation, 1 expandable folder (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Alpha/Chron file 2001 (Box 8)
  - Alpha/Chron file 2002 (Box 8)
  - Clippings and press releases, pre- 1987-1991, 6 folders (Box 8)
    (photocopies)
  - Miscellaneous press releases (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 8)
  - Briefing books for meetings with Governor Engler
    - Meeting date September 24, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Meeting date March 28, 2001 (Box 8)
  - Office web site, December 20, 2002 (Box 8)
    (on CD-ROM; located in CD storage)